Over the next maybe six to 12 months, I
think the market will start becoming a
little bit more impatient to say where
is this benefit coming from because
we're investing hundreds of billions of
dollars. Where is the return on
investment in that respect?
>> Welcome. I'm Manita Huja, editor at
large at Forbes and founder of
Iconoclast. We're here at the NASDAQ
market site with our series sponsor,
Manual Life. Joining us now, Colin
Perie, global chief investment officer
for public markets and manual life
investment management. Colin, thank you
so much for joining us.
>> Thank you.
>> So, Manual Life has been actively
investing in scaling AI capabilities
from nearly a decade, way before it was
in vogue. But recently, you guys just
unleashed your new AI research platform
and how it's So, we're here to talk
about how it's enhancing the firm's
global investment strategies.
>> Indeed. Yes.
It's something we're really excited
about at this point in time. And of
course, a lot of people are talking
about AI and we're really excited about
the opportunities in in the investment
space right now.
>> I think I was reading the FT this
morning and it seems like the US economy
is all AI. I think we were just talking
about that right before we got started
as well. And Forbes, we put out our own
AI research survey and we found that 97%
of seuite executives plan to increase
their budget for AI implementation in
the coming year. And so talk to me a
little bit about manual life and how
that presents an opportunity with this
new capabilities that you're sharing
with the market now.
>> Absolutely. We'd love to. AI is
transformative. It's exciting. It's
changing industries and and it's
changing the investment management
industry as well and and and manual life
want to be at the forefront of that.
When you think ultimately about what we
do as investors, we invest in companies,
we invest in countries, we invest in all
these different entities. It's about
data. It's about understanding markets.
It's about understanding the different
investment opportunities that we have
and AI really allows us to broaden our
understanding of the multitude sources
of data that we have globally. So it
allows us using our new AI research
assistant to really package together the
information to source it to understand
it to populate templates um and then
obviously to try and inform some of our
analysis and and you know explore some
investment opportunities. And I love how
you guys call it an AI research
assistant because when you think about
investing, it is such a personal
experience, right, for the enduser and
the client and uh the companies that you
deal with and investors, they need to
know that they're they're working with
the experts that are at Manual Life as
well. So, I love how you're utilizing it
as a tool, but it's not, you know,
detracting from the human experience in
any way.
>> Absolutely. One of the central tenets to
our policy is that the the human
judgment, the human is still at the core
of our process and that's something that
doesn't doesn't change with AI. What we
what we want AI to be doing is is the
repetitive work, the the data sourcing,
the data understanding and uh as I say
templating uh in a quicker time than
than our analysts would would be able to
do.
>> But then we want our analysts to look at
the the outputs to look at to markets
and to put their emphasis into
investment decisions. at that point,
their focus in in that area because
that's the value ad piece. That's where
our clients want us
>> uh and our people to concentrate and to
focus and you know that that's really
what we're we're trying to do here. It's
about getting the information,
understanding it better and then you
know ultimately as well getting to
market quicker with some of our
decisions.
>> So increasing efficiencies.
>> Absolutely. Yes.
>> So anytime a new technology is developed
obviously it's human nature there's
usually a bit of acclamation period
right. tell us how you introduced this
to your team and your bottomup approach
to how you're presenting this into the
marketplace.
>> Sure. I mean, you you say introduction,
I would say it was a a bit of
co-creation more than anything.
>> What we wanted to do right from the
start here was ensure that there was no
silos between our AI teams and our
investment teams or any of the the rest
of the workforce
>> and to make sure that there was deep
collaboration going on. So uh rather
than have the AI team uh try and sit you
know away from our investment teams to
try and build tools and then bring them
and essentially try and sell them to the
investment teams
>> um we started at first foundations we
asked the AI team to sit with the
investment teams to be embedded with
them to understand what they do on a
day-to-day basis to understand what
problems that they have what they'd like
to solve how can they add value with
some of the tools that we could build
and from there we co-created the tools
so it was very much dem demand led from
the investment teams and the result of
that was that the adoption was that much
greater. It was that much quicker
because these weren't tools that came in
from left field. These were tools that
were solving problems that the
investment teams had at that point. They
worked on the creation and then they
valued the output that we got from these
tools. So it's almost like you work
through that trial and error process at
the outset of the process instead of
introducing it to clients or your team
and then integrating it. Right.
>> I think that's right. And one of the
advantages that we have is as I say we
have an AI team but we don't um you know
we people come from a you know diverse
uh range of backgrounds. We've got some
CF charter holders in the team. We've
got some quant resources. We've got some
AI experts. But they understand
investment. they work with the
investment teams and as a result of that
they understand what we're trying to
achieve with our AI tools and ultimately
what our clients are looking for to to
deliver in that respect. Um and so
therefore that co-creation has worked
really really well for us.
>> So it sounds like the opportunity was
understood right away and the
efficiencies kind of came into play.
Correct.
>> I think the opportunity at a high level
was understood straight away. I think
one of the interesting things is across
any company and across any group of
people there are those that are very
early adopters and there are those that
take some time and I think that uh you
know one of the benefits of the process
that we've undertaken is that there were
indeed some people who were probably a
little bit cynical at times and said how
is this going to impact me how is this
going to help me do my job by being
involved in the process by being
involved in the creation of the tools
they've seen the power that this
technology has they've seen how it can
add benefit to what they're doing on a
day-to-day basis. So, as a result of
that, we uh we not only saw a very high
uptick from, you know, the people that
really believed in this from the start,
but we we've seen a significant shift in
some in the attitude of some people who
have, I would say, have gone from
cynical to super users in actually a
relatively short period of time.
>> I love that. From cynical to super user.
So, they actually got agency um over
over the product because they co-created
it.
>> Indeed. So, now that we've kind of laid
the groundwork for the opportunity set
and how this is making um investing more
efficient for your clients and
customers, talk to me a little bit about
some of the concerns that maybe came to
the four as you started to develop this
and you started to test it in the
market.
>> Sure. And let me just say yes,
efficiencies, but also value ad and
that's a really important concept as
well in the investment management piece.
>> Uh what concerns did we have? Well,
there was a couple. Number one is one
that impacts every company uh when
they're looking at AI and developing
tools which is do we build or do we buy
and that was something that we were very
conscious of because this is technology
as you know that is developing extremely
fast it changes every day we've seen the
investment that's going into AI um and
there is a concern that if you build
something it may be redundant by the
time you've actually brought it to
market so that was one of the concerns
that we had and we've really adopted a
hybrid approach We do, as I've outlined,
build some of our own tools. Um, and we
do fast prototypes. We try and bring
things to market quickly. Um, and we
only scale it where we see that there's
a true benefit to it. And that means
that there is some redundancy in some of
the things that we've built and that's
absolutely accepted. Um, in other areas,
you know, you can look to to buy in uh
the technology as well. So, the build or
buy is one thing. The other thing which
was very important to us as well is that
AI is additive to what we're doing. We
have a very long history uh very strong
processes at manual life investment
management and we didn't want to bring
in something that would disrupt that
that would maybe change or or would look
to you know enforce change on some of
those investment processes. So we really
wanted to make sure that the tools that
we're using that we're bringing in are
complementaryary to our bottom-up
fundamental research uh process. Um and
indeed that's what we've developed. But
obviously going through this at all
times, we want to ensure that the tools
that we're bringing in are absolutely
right for the processes and the teams
and the strategies that we're running to
ultimately value add value for our
clients.
>> So it sounds like there was no not much
of a disruption as you integrated this,
right? So that probably helped a lot
with the buyin process, right? I think I
read that 65% of your public markets
investment team uses this AI research
assistant. Correct.
>> That's correct. That that was a point in
time uh measurement and that is is is
constantly increasing. We're seeing
we're seeing global um adoption uh go
forward and increase at all times as
people get to understand the tools, they
get to use the tools and then they get
to develop them further. So the uptake
has actually been ahead off the targets
that we set originally and we're
continuing to see uh not just from the
investment management teams but across
the business people looking at the tools
that we've developed seeing how they can
add value uh to to their processes and
and their workflow on a daily basis and
so we're seeing increased adoption
across the firm which is obviously
fantastic for us to see.
>> So that's great from the firm
perspective. What are you hearing from
clients? Has this been introduced to
clients as of yet? So we we we've um we
we have obviously been speaking to
clients. We've been speaking to media
about what we're doing in this space and
and and clients are certainly very
interested. They're very excited. I
think that if we said to clients that we
weren't doing anything in this space, I
think they would actually uh be more
concerned
>> fair point
>> than if we're saying what we're doing.
So what we're trying to demonstrate to
clients and and this goes back to the
point before around we we're not
delegating decision-m and that still
very much lies with our uh our human
workforce. They are the decision makers.
They are the value adders. Markets can
be a rationale and and so we need
clients to understand and clients very
much want to see that you know the tools
we're developing are adding to the
process. to helping, as I say, go deeper
in research, broader across markets,
hopefully exploring and uncovering more
investment opportunities,
but embedded within our existing
processes, within our existing teams,
and then we still have those skilled and
experienced portfolio managers and
analysts who can then take that
information and apply it in the best way
for those client outcomes. So, I think
clients are excited. They want us to
continue pushing down this road and see
what else can happen so we can add more
value for them. Um but it's something
that is continually evolving and so I
think they're sort of saying what next
>> right and speaking of evolving one
consistent narrative that we're all
dealing with across all industries and
sectors as we think about AI media not
excluded is the fear that AI may take
you know XYZ jobs away from an industry
is that something that you have to kind
of uh manage internally and also you
know as you continue to roll out this
product
>> I think that's A that's certainly a
narrative across the market. Um and and
and you see it in in in in media almost
on a daily basis right now.
>> We were very clear at the outset when we
were speaking to our teams that uh you
know essentially we were saying we're
going to give you the tools to stop
doing the things that you probably don't
even really enjoy doing. There was you
know more repetitive data heavy tasks
>> and we're going to give you the
opportunity to spend more time on the
value ad which is where you take those
investment ideas and put them into the
market. So for us, it hasn't changed
what the teams are doing. It's just
changing how they're doing it and where
they're focusing their time. Um, and you
know, for us, it's very important that
we continue to invest in our people as
well as our technology um, in order to,
you know, drive both forward in tandem.
So I'm sure you've been unveiling also
more AI trainings throughout the firm
and giving people that upskilling at the
same time so that they feel like they're
adding to their work experience and you
know their viability in a continuously
changing global economy.
>> I think that's absolutely right and uh
if you look at you know the the the the
younger uh inflow of people coming into
the firm they've got a different skill
set than maybe investors had 20 years
ago. there is more of a reliance on
technology in work now and I think that
you know as a firm what we want to do is
we want to meet um you know our
employees desires in this area we want
to ensure that if they want to lean into
AI and AI development we've got
specialist teams and we're working
together with those teams if they just
want to benefit from the tools then
obviously we're set up for that as well
but certainly from an employment
perspective we know that people are
interested in this we know in the same
way that emails and smartphones have
come along and have been embedded into
everyday life. AI is going to do the
same. AI is doing the same. And so
people do want to learn um how to use
the tools. They do want to upskill and
we need to give them a platform to do
that. And and that's what we're doing at
Manual Life Investment Management.
>> So I recently had a conversation on this
topic. It was adjacent with the dean of
Wharton, Erica James, and it was really
interesting as they're kind of preparing
this next generation for AI. She said
one thing that is under uh undervalued
is actually the soft skills come into
play in such a volatile global economy
where AI is coming to the forefront is
being flexible and just being able to
adapt to changing environments and then
integrate this technology. Uh it's
almost impossible to prepare in school
or even in the workforce because to your
point AI is changing so quickly. But one
of the things that she's seeing that's a
marker for success in this era is just
that adaptability. So quick question for
you. In the future, do you think
individuals will be able to have a
successful career in investment
management without the use of AI or do
you think that this is the new status
quo, the new normal?
>> I don't think AI is going to go away.
Um, so I think that AI across all
industries and sectors is here to stay.
And I think that uh you know when you
look at the individuals that you're
talking about clearly for an investment
management role we're looking for EQ
we're looking for IQ. So AI is going to
play a part in that but it's not going
to play the whole part. It's going to
play some of that part. And as I
mentioned earlier um you know having
been in markets for far too long now we
all know that they're irrational. Um and
you do need that human element. You need
to be adaptable. You need to be uh
resolute. You need to be resilient. um
and you need to uh understand, you know,
when when to take risk and when not to
take risk, etc. These are things that
are very difficult to to teach. They
tend to be more on the job. We'll use AI
to give us more confidence in making
some of those decisions, but ultimately
we'll still be looking for the people
that have the personality types in order
to take those decisions for the benefit
of our clients. So AI is not going to be
everything to everyone everywhere.
>> Um but it, as I say, it is here. It is
going to stay, it is going to play a
part. And so I think that in order to
uncover those investment decisions and
and opportunities to position us best,
we will be using it uh going forward uh
you know in in in everinccreasing ways.
>> Well said. So as investors you guys are
have a fiduciary responsibility to your
clients and regulators. How are you
ensuring that you and the manual life
team are scaling and implementing AI
responsibly? That's another narrative
that we're seeing in the marketplace a
lot.
>> Yes, it is and it's something that
obviously we have to ensure every day.
So, uh you mentioned fiduciary
responsibility. I mean first and
foremost from a from a holistic
perspective that is something that
covers every one of us on a on a daily
basis at manual life and and within the
financial sector we have a fiduciary
duty to our clients and to our
regulators and that's to you know uh
apply and adhere to the highest ethical
standards in everything that we do. So
that covers everything. Um more
specifically when we think about Gen AI
and tool development, we have um you
know model risk committee. So where we
uh build something new um that's got to
be run through that model risk committee
which is filled with experts from our
compliance from our risk teams from AI
teams and from from other teams as well.
So they have to get the sign off before
we're allowed to use them. And so um you
know we do that on an ongoing basis uh
that makes sure that you know with the
modeling that we're bringing in it's
appropriate it's been tested at that
point in time and then as we go forward
we'll obviously be conducting ongoing
tests to make sure that models are
behaving like we thought they would
ensure that you know are they are we
uncovering any biases over times or in
certain market conditions are they
deviating behaviorally from anything
that we thought and if so then obviously
we can pull that back uh and we can
reapply in that instance. as well. So
there's a number of different layers
that we apply to ensure that we are
adhering to that fiduciary
responsibility.
>> And I was just thinking about how long
I've been covering the investment
management industry and the alternative
space. It used to be that these
so-called quant funds or funds that had
access to these algorithms were the
secret black box that were able to
execute, you know, head and shoulders
above the rest of the market and the
other players. In many ways, this is
evening the playing field, right? Well,
what we know about AI is it's
disruptive. It's disruptive across
industries and it's disruptive within
industries. And we're seeing evidence of
that on an ongoing basis from a markets
perspective. Clearly earlier this year
with the news from Deep Seek in China,
>> um we saw some huge market ramifications
coming through at that point in time.
And so, you know, the argument there
could be yes, this is this is leveling
the playing field in that respect. Um
there's a lot of capital expenditure
that's going into AI. So that's going to
provide some advantages to those with
potentially the ability to invest
further, but ultimately it can be and it
has been democratized and and and that
can certainly as you say level up the
playing field in certain instances. So
it it makes it interesting and I think
it what's you know the most interesting
is nobody really knows right and as a
result of that you know there there are
still questions and there'll still be
developments that people cannot foresee
at this point in time. And again, that's
to Dean James's point too from Wharton
too is that because nobody really knows
that in and of itself is leveling the
playing field in terms of, you know, uh,
who can get ahead and how quickly. And
you spoke about ramifications. Talk to
me a little bit more. You touched on
this about managing all the risks
associated with AI. Do you do a lot of
stress testing? And if so, what does
that look like?
>> Yeah. So, I think there's a couple of
ways that you can we can answer that
question. The first one is obviously
from a risk perspective we invest in
markets and we invest in in industries
and areas indeed most areas which are
now being impacted by AI. So um you know
we're constantly uh looking at some of
the risks that come through in that
whenever we make an investment we never
have 100% of the information anyway. So
we're used to managing that risk in
terms of that respect. Um and it's
something that that we'll continue to do
and clearly where we have uh gaps in our
information set if we can't fill those
in then it's often something that we'll
step back from.
>> From a company perspective as I say uh
there's a lot of AI development uh tools
that we have uh that ensure that we are
trying to identify those risks trying to
identify uh you know where we have these
fiduciary responsibilities what we need
to do about them to make sure that you
know we adhere to those high standards.
So from a both a markets perspective but
also from a company perspective there
are risks but you know investment
management is about risk management. So
we feel we've got them fairly well
covered.
>> So we're almost out of time. I have a
couple of quick last you know final
questions. What's one AI trend that
you're keeping track of and why? Maybe
outside of your AI research assistant
but more broadly speaking. I think
broadly um every day it seems we get
news of more investment into AI.
Hundreds of billions of dollars are
being invested into AI. What we've seen
so far is what I'd call the enablers who
are, you know, those at the forefront of
AI, the chip makers, the data centers,
uh some of the physical security, etc.
Those investments have benefited. The
beneficiaries, which is pretty much
everyone else, haven't necessarily
benefited as much. the reaction has been
a bit muted. At some point, the
investment that we're seeing, the
capital expenditure that goes into the
market, we are going to have to see some
of that, you know, being realized in
terms of benefits and value for
companies. I'd say we haven't really
seen that right now. Over the next maybe
6 to 12 months, I think the market will
start becoming a little bit more
impatient to say where is this benefit
coming from because we're investing
hundreds of billions of dollars.
>> Where is the return on investment in
that respect? So, that's something that
we are keeping a very keen eye on.
>> That's such an interesting point. So
some final thoughts. Talk to me about
the ROI that you hope to see over the
next five years from Manual Life's AI
research assistant.
>> So I think it's it's return on
investment. It's going to be very
difficult to put a number on these
things because as as we've said a on a
number of occasions, this is a fast
flowing area. So you know what what we
do know is that we'll continue to invest
here. um you know my ultimate objective
is to add value for my for my clients to
ensure that from an investment
perspective we're meeting their
objectives um AI is going to play its
part in that. So ultimately in three
five years time we'll hopefully be using
AI and the benefits of AI along with
everything else that we do within our
processes to deliver that value. If we
can deliver that investment outcome for
our clients then that's certainly a
great return on investment um that we'd
be very happy with.
>> Okay, final question. What's one piece
of advice you have for seuite executives
who are hesitant maybe about integrating
and implementing AI into their workforce
and into their work processes going
forward.
>> I think the the advice would simply be
that you just have to embrace the
uncertainty. It is something from what
we've seen at manual life it is so
powerful the ability to add value into
all areas of the company all areas of
your process. It's definitely there. Um,
it's going to change. You probably won't
get it all right. Um, as I say, we've
developed some things and thrown them
away. We've developed some things and
they're amazing and we're going to keep
and and drive them forward. Um, we don't
know where it's going to go exactly in
in the next 3 to 5 years. The technology
will continue to change. But if you
don't embrace that uncertainty, then I
think, you know, there is a fear
certainly in certain areas, certain
industries, you will be left behind. And
you don't want to be in that position in
in in that time period, I'd say. So it's
better to move fast and break things
like Mark Zuckerberg said, right?
>> I think that's right. Yeah.
>> All right. Well, Colin Perie, manual
life investment management, thank you so
much for joining us.
>> Thank you.
>> I'm Ben Auja, editor at large at Forbes
and founder of Iconoclass. And this is
Iconoclast at the NASDAQ market site.